Department of Spanish and Latin American Studies fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Department of Spanish and Latin American Studies fonds
1967 - 1996
F-106
63 cm of textual records
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
Department of Spanish and Latin American Studies
The Department of Spanish and Latin American Studies was created in 1988 as a merger between the Spanish Language Program of the Department of Literature, Languages and Linguistics and the Latin American Studies Program of the Faculty of Arts. The department was abolished in 1996.
In February 1971 a Latin American Studies Program was proposed to Senate. This program was first under the jurisdiction of the Division of General Studies in 1972, and then placed in the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies upon the inception of that faculty at the end of 1972. It was the first area studies minor at SFU and served as a model for the creation of similar programs in Canadian and Africa-Middle East Studies, also administered the Dean of FIDS. By 1984, Latin American Studies had evolved from granting an area studies minor to granting joint major degrees in conjunction with six other arts disciplines (Archaeology, Geography, History, Political Science, Spanish, and Sociology and Anthropology). The field school, first held in Guatemala in 1976, generated additional interest in the program. The LAS Student Union organized film series and other events. With the dissolution of FIDS in 1985. the program became part of the Faculty of Arts until the creation of the Department of Spanish and Latin American Studies in 1988.
Spanish language instruction at SFU took place first in the Department of Modern Languages, established in 1965, and later renamed the Department of Languages, Literature, and Linguistics in 1978 to reflect its broader scholarly focus. In 1988, the department was disbanded and instruction in Spanish language and literature was transferred to the Department of Spanish and Latin American Studies.
Upon the dissolution of the Department of Spanish and Latin American Studies, Spanish language instruction was transferred to the Language Training Institute in the Faculty of Arts. The Latin American Studies program was placed in the Department of Sociology and Anthropology in the Faculty of Arts. For further information on the dissolution of the department, see the appendix (Simon Fraser News, June 20, 1996).
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of its creator.
The fonds consists of records relating primarily to the activities of the department and its predecessor programs. Activities and events documented include the evolution of the department, deliberations of departmental committees, correspondence of the director, course instruction including the field school, the role of the LAS student union, and the presentation of special events such as speakers and films.
The arrangement of the fonds into series and subseries was provided by the archivist in December 2003.
Gomez-Moriana, Dr. Antonio; Garcia, Dr. Jorge
The records were acquired by the Archives through the application of University Records Retention Schedules and Disposal Authorities (RRSDAs).
All accessions have been processed as of February 2006. No further accruals are expected.
The records were held by the Department of Spanish and Latin American Studies and the Area Studies Office of the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies.
Records relating to the predecessor programs of the school are found in F-13, the Department of Languages, Literature and Linguistics, and F 23, the Faculty of Interdisciplinary Studies (F-23-3-1-7, F-23-3-1-8). For further details, consult the individual series descriptions.
Some files may contain personal or confidential information. Access to these files may be restricted as required by law. Files marked 'pending review' must be reviewed by an archivist prior to release, and as a result of the review access restrictions may apply. Please see the file lists and consult the archivist for more details.
File lists are available.
- Department history and structure files, 1973 - 1993; F-106-1; 9 cm of textual records
  published
  Series consists of records relating to the development of the two programs that eventually merged to form the Department of Spanish and Latin American Studies. Activities and events documented include curriculum development, program and department proposals, and reporting of courses and events.
  Records include correspondence, reports, proposals, publications and other documents.
  - LAS program report, 1973; F-106-1-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
    Textual records
    Pending review
  - LAS joint major proposal, 1983 - 1984; F-106-1-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
  - LAS curriclulum changes, 1984; F-106-1-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
  - LAS program development, 1984; F-106-1-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
  - Proposal - International Studies planning committee, 1986; F-106-1-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
  - LAS program - FIDS, 1984 - 1988; F-106-1-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
  - Proposal for SLAS department establishment, 1979 - 1987; F-106-1-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
  - Spanish Division - regulations and important papers, 1981 - 1986; F-106-1-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
  - Open letter to Spanish students, 1985; F-106-1-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
  - Proposal for dissolution of DLLL, 1987; F-106-1-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
  - Proposal for Department of Spanish and Latin American Studies, 1986 - 1988; F-106-1-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
  - Publications, 1988 - 1993; F-106-1-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
    Open
- Committee files, 1970 - 1989; F-106-2; 16 cm of textual records
  Series consists primarily of records relating to the meetings and deliberations of committees of the predecessor programs of the Department of Spanish and Latin American Studies although the first few departmental meetings of SLAS are included in the Latin American Studies Steering Committee minutes. Records include committee agendas, minutes, and supporting papers. President's Advisory Committee on University Priorities (PACUP) committee files include correspondence.
  Each committee has been assigned a separate sub-series. Committees have been grouped into the following types: LAS committees, Spanish Division and DLLL committees, and PACUP.
  Additional records relating to Spanish division meetings, plenary meetings, and committee of chairmen meetings in the Department of Literature, Languages and Linguistics are found in F-13-1-4; F-13-1-47; and F-13-1-8 respectively.
  - LAS Steering Committee, 1971 - 1989; F-106-2-1; 2 cm of textual records
    - LAS Steering Committee minutes, vol. 1, 1971 - 1989; F-106-2-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
    - LAS Steering Committee minutes, vol. 2, 1971 - 1989; F-106-2-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
    - LAS Steering Committee minutes, vol. 3, 1971 - 1989; F-106-2-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
  - DLLL - Spanish Division, 1970 - 1988; F-106-2-2; 5 cm of textual records
    - DLLL - Spanish Division minutes, 1970 - 1973; F-106-2-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
    - DLLL - Spanish Division minutes, 1975 - 1979; F-106-2-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 106-1)
    - DLLL - Spanish Division minutes, vol. 1, 4 January 1980 - 4 February 1988; F-106-2-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 106-2)
    - DLLL - Spanish Division minutes, vol. 2, 4 January 1980 - 4 February 1988; F-106-2-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 106-2)
    - DLLL - Spanish Division minutes, vol. 3, 4 January 1980 - 4 February 1988; F-106-2-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 106-2)
  - DLLL - Spanish Division - Faculty only meetings, 1983 - 1988; F-106-2-3; 1 cm of textual records
    - DLLL - Spanish Division - Faculty only meetings, 1983 - 1988; F-106-2-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 106-2)
  - DLLL - Committee of Chairmen, 1982 - 1983; F-106-2-4; 1 cm of textual records
    - DLLL - Committee of Chairmen minutes, 1982 - 1983; F-106-2-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 106-2)
  - DLLL- Plenary meetings, 1982 - 1983; F-106-2-5; 1 cm of textual records
    - DLLL - Plenary meetings minutes, 1982 - 1983; F-106-2-5-0-1 (Archival box - standard 106-2)
  - DLLL - Executive Committee, 1986; F-106-2-6; 1 cm of textual records
    - DLLL - Executive Committee, 1986; F-106-2-6-0-1 (Archival box - standard 106-2)
  - President's Advisory Committee on University Priorities (PCAUP) - LAS, 1975 - 1984; F-106-2-7; 5 cm of textual records
    - PACUP - LAS, 1984; F-106-2-7-0-1 (Archival box - standard 106-2)
    - PACUP correspondence - LAS, 1984; F-106-2-7-0-2 (Archival box - standard 106-2)
    - PACUP draft materials - LAS, 1984; F-106-2-7-0-3 (Archival box - standard 106-2)
    - PACUP Spanish Division DLLL, 1975 - 1984; F-106-2-7-0-4 (Archival box - standard 106-2)
- Departmental correspondence, 1987 - 1989; F-106-3; 1 cm of textual records
  Series consists of the Chair's correspondence with University administration and other departments. Activities and events documented include budget preparation, conference planning, and program development. Records include correspondence, publications, and a single issue of the departmental newsletter.
  - Spanish and Latin American Studies departmental correspondence - general, 1987 - 1989; F-106-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 106-3)
- Curriculum and instruction files, 1967 - 1996; F-106-4; 15 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to the instruction offered by the Department of Latin American Studies and its predecessor programs. Series consists primarily of course files as well as a list of DLLL graduands and a history of LAS course enrollment. Records include course outlines, notes, posters, and exam questions.
  - DLLL - graduands, 1967 - 1983; F-106-4-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 106-3)
  - DLLL - Spanish course offerings, 1976 - 1988; F-106-4-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 106-3)
  - Spanish Division memo to Faculty of Arts Curriculum Committee, 1985 - 1986; F-106-4-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 106-3)
  - LAS course posters, 1974 - 1984; F-106-4-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 106-3)
  - LAS - history of course enrolment, 1976 - 1982; F-106-4-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 106-3)
  - LAS - content courses, 1979 - 1984; F-106-4-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 106-3)
  - LAS 100-3 - Introduction to Latin American Studies, 1971 - 1977; F-106-4-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 106-3)
  - LAS 140-3 - Pre-Columbia/Hispanic Heritage, 1987 - 1988; F-106-4-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 106-3)
  - LAS 200-3 - Introduction to Latin American Culture, 1973 - 1978; F-106-4-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 106-3)
  - LAS 200-3 - Introduction to Latin American Culture, 1979 - 1987; F-106-4-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 106-3)
  - LAS 200-3 - Introduction to Latin American Issues, 1987 - 1988; F-106-4-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 106-3)
  - LAS 312-3 - Latin American Cultural Topics, 1987; F-106-4-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 106-3)
  - LAS 402-5 - Special Topics Courses in Latin American Studies, 1972 - 1983; F-106-4-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 106-3)
  - LAS 403-5 - Special Topics Courses in Latin American Studies, 1972 - 1988; F-106-4-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 106-4)
  - LAS 404-5 - Special Topics Courses in Latin American Studies, 1973 - 1980; F-106-4-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 106-4)
  - Department of Spanish and Latin American Studies - course offerings, 1989; F-106-4-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 106-4)
  - LAS course posters (oversize), 1972 - 1996; F-106-4-0-0-17
- Field school files, 1977 - 1988; F-106-5; 12 cm of textual records
  Starting in 1977 in Guatemala, the Latin American Studies program operated field schools during the summer in various countries. Subsequent field schools were held in Guatemala in 1978 and 1979; in Peru in 1981; in Mexico in 1983 and 1985; and in Cuba in 1988. The field schools provided courses and tours to local archaeological, historical, and tourist sites. Series consists of records relating to the operation of the field schools.
  Records include brochures, program descriptions and schedules, course outlines, progress and final reports, correspondence, lists of participants, and other documents.
  - Field School - Guatemala, 1977; F-106-5-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 106-4)
  - Field School - Guatemala, 1978; F-106-5-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 106-4)
  - Field School - Guatemala, 1979; F-106-5-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 106-4)
  - Field School - Peru, 1981; F-106-5-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 106-4)
  - Field School - Mexico, 1983; F-106-5-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 106-4)
  - Field School - Mexico, vol. 1, 1985; F-106-5-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 106-4)
  - Field School - Mexico, vol. 2, 1985; F-106-5-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 106-4)
  - Field School - Mexico evaluations, vol. 3, 1985; F-106-5-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
  - Field School - Cuba, 1988; F-106-5-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
  - Field School - FIDS correspondence, 1982 - 1988; F-106-5-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
  - Field School funding - Bridge to Future Campaign, 1985 - 1986; F-106-5-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
- Student union files, 1982 - 1985; F-106-6; 2 cm of textual records
  Series consists of files relating to the activities of the Latin American Studies Student Union (LASSU). Activities and events documented include the presentation of cultural events and a course proposal put forward by LASSU. Records include news clippings, posters, correspondence, and newsletters.
  - FIDS - LAS student representative, 1982 - 1983; F-106-6-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
  - LAS Student Union - general, 1983 - 1985; F-106-6-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
  - LAS Student Union - course proposal, 1984; F-106-6-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
- Special events files, 1977 - 1989; F-106-7; 7 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to public events sponsored by the Latin American Studies program and the Spanish Division of the Department of Literature, Languages, and Linguistics. Activities and events documented include lectures, film series, musical presentations, and conferences. Records include posters, correspondence, brochures, news clippings, and a report on the Spanish-speaking community in greater Vancouver.
  - LAS - special events, 1977 - 1986; F-106-7-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
  - LAS - Noam Chomsky visit, 1983 - 1984; F-106-7-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
  - LAS - Liberation Theology Conference, 1986; F-106-7-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
    Open, no restrictions
    Access review (Jul 10, 2023) – File is open, no restricted information identified.
  - LAS - Human rights and the disappeared, 1988; F-106-7-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
  - SLAS - Brazilian Film series, 1989; F-106-7-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
  - Report on Spanish-speaking community in Vancouver, 1977; F-106-7-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
  - DLLL - Spanish Division - guest speakers, 1981 - 1984; F-106-7-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
  - DLLL - Spanish Division - special events, 1983 - 1986; F-106-7-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 106-5)
  - DLLL - Spanish Division - open house, 1984 - 1985; F-106-7-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 106-5)